<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>OSCG</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 14:57:03 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 14:57:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Science Community Galway - Second Meeting 21 Jan 2020</title>
        <description>Early Adopters Meeting
Register here if you want to join the Open Science Community Galway
What will happen at this meeting?
This will be the very first meeting of Open enthusiasts in Galway. It will be nice to connect enthusiasts from across NUI Galway campus and beyond. We will do that in an informal and friendly manner over (free) pizza.

Among first things we might like to talk about are:


  Where are we on the step-by-step guide from OSC Utrecht?
  How should OSCG members communicate? (Website, Twitter, Teams/WhatsApp etc.)
  What are our next steps (events, recruiting more members etc.)?


Sounds interesting? Join us!

Among first things we might like to talk about are our ambition and next steps. More practical things might be the OSCG website, communication and first events.

If you want to get involved please let us know by using this form. Everyone welcome!

Where is the workshop 
NUI Galway, Arts Millennium Building - AM 207 (CELT Training Room)








</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/event/2020/01/21/OSCG-meeting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/event/2020/01/21/OSCG-meeting/</guid>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        
        <category>Event</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Scanathon. Crowd-sourced digitisation</title>
        <description>Scanathon. Crowd-sourced digitisation

Register here

Description
Using the NUIG Library’s recently acquired ScanTent, (developed as part of the READ  project, for more information, see https://scantent.eu/en/ ), and our  trustee SLR cameras, this event will see participants divided into  teams. The event will be a race to see which piece of equipment copes  better with rapid digitisation, with lighting, clarity, processing  speed, and image quality for the web weighted as the measures of  success.

There will also be spot prizes for rapid fire rounds of  digitisation, finding a gremlin in the collection of archives you are  working on, and more besides!

In the workshop, we will work  together to digitise and publish a collection of archives for the web.  The output will be a crowd-sourced piece of work that opens up a  collection of archives to the wider world for research and consultation.
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/event/2020/01/14/Library-Scanathon/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/event/2020/01/14/Library-Scanathon/</guid>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        
        <category>Event</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Our first OSCG Meeting!</title>
        <description>OSCG Meeting 25 November 2019
Here is a brief summary of the First OSCG Meeting - ever!

Welcome everyone!
17 people attended our First Meeting. A very good turnout! I haven’t quite figured out how to embed images on a blog post but you can see some pictures at our OSCGalway Twitter profile. Special thanks to Fiona Concannon from CELT who helped with the room! Anyone who wants to look at the introductory slides that I used they are here.

Thinking about OSCG Principles
At some point in the near future we might need to formalise this but it seems  that key principles of our Community are:


  open to everyone in Galway
  inclusive (with regards to disciplines, aspects of open Scholarship, seniority etc.)
  researcher-led.


What does Open Scholarship mean?
This is an important and ongoing discussion. Our concept of Open Scholarship is based on the Open Science Policy Framework of the EU Commission but we need to adapt it to the needs of our Community. There were some interesting comments on scope and wording of the Eight Pillars.

You can see the latest version of the Eight Pillars here.

What is next for OSCG?
This is early days but we are thinking about the following:


  Open Scholarship Community Galway members meetings. The next one will be in the second half of January. Interested in coming along? Sign up here: http://bit.ly/OSCGalwayInterest
  Open Scholarship Café. A semi-formal meeting 4-6 times per year with topics sourced from the Community, such as data sharing, open source software, data visualisation, Text &amp;amp; Data Mining, journal clubs, open textbooks, open publishing…
  Open Scholarship Week 2020. A series of events in early May. More details to follow soon


</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/11/28/First-OSCG-Meeting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/11/28/First-OSCG-Meeting/</guid>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        
        <category>Blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Science Community Galway - Meeting 21 January 2020</title>
        <description>OSCG January 2020 Meeting
Register here if you want to join the Open Science Community Galway

What will happen at this meeting?
This will be the second meeting of Open enthusiasts in Galway. It is still early days for our Community so we need to talk some basics such as members communication and our website.

On the agenda:


  Update from Monica (@monzc) on the NUI Galway Library negotiations with big publishers
  Elaine (@ElaineToomey1) and Hardy (@HardySchwamm) on the Open Scholarship Week 2020.
  Catherine (@catherinecronin) on Open Education and the National Forum


Sounds interesting? Join us!

We hold our meetings in an inclusive and friendly manner over (free) pizza. New Open enthusiasts are always welcome!

If you want to get involved please let us know by using this form.

Where is the meeting ?



NUI Galway, Arts Millennium Building - AM 207 (CELT Training Room)








</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/event/2019/11/25/Second-OSCG-meeting/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/event/2019/11/25/Second-OSCG-meeting/</guid>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        
        <category>Event</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OpenStreetMap workshop</title>
        <description>OpenStreetMap workshop
Register here
Description
The Insight Centre for Data Analytics at NUI Galway is hosting a workshop Saturday November 23rd for community groups, environmentalists, science researchers, geographers, planners and students to learn about and participate in OpenStreetMapping, a free, editable map of the whole world that is being built by volunteers. The underlying electronic data is open-sourced and crowd-sourced.

Organised by Ireland’s OpenStreetMap (OSM) community, the free event is open to all interested individuals and groups and will commence from 11am at the Insight Centre of the Data Science Institute in the Dangan Business Park.

This information and workshop event, taking place as part of our centre’s Citizen Science schedule, will provide a wonderful opportunity for both experts and novices to exchange ideas and experiences on this very important grassroots global initiative.
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 23 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/event/2019/11/23/OpenStreetMap-workshop-Copy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/event/2019/11/23/OpenStreetMap-workshop-Copy/</guid>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        
        <category>Event</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Julia programming language</title>
        <description>Julia workshop 

  Agenda
  What to bring?
  What to install?
  Other links and education content
  Organizers
  Where is the workshop


Agenda 
09:30-10:15: Session 1: Introduction 
10:15-11:00: Session 2: Data structures and flow control 
11:00-11:20: Break 
11:20-12:10: Session 3: Types, macros and packages 
12:10-13:00: Session 4: Julia internals and distributed computing 
13:00-14:00: Lunch (not provided suggested location is the Friars restaurant on campus)  
14:00-15:30: Session 5: Plotting, performance tuning and examples 
15:30-16:00: Break 
16:00-17:00: Session 6: Use case examples

Back to top

What to bring 
Please bring the following:

  Your own laptop
  An extension cord if you have one handy (the nearest power outlet might not be right at the table)


Back to top

What to install 
No specific installation instructions are given for this workshop and the workshop may involve online tutorials which do not require a full installation. Users who are keen to set-up a full installation/environment for Julia can follow the steps below: 
1) Download Julia and look at the installation instructions for your platform.  
2) Download and install the Atom editor (which will function as the IDE for Julia). 
3) Install the Juno package in Atom which helps to set-up Atom to function as the IDE for Julia.

Back to top

Additional links and educational resources 
1) The julia learning website features additional training/learning resources.  
2) JuliaAcademy offers free introductory courses/tutorials as well.

Back to top

Course organizers 

  Dr Niall Madden, School of Mathematics, Statistics and Applied Mathematics, NUIG
  Kevin Moerman, School of Engineering, Biomedical Engineering, NUIG_
  ICHEC: The Irish Centre for High-End Computing


Back to top

Where is the workshop 
NUIG CA107 Aras Cairnes








Back to top
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/event/2019/11/06/Julia-workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/event/2019/11/06/Julia-workshop/</guid>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        
        <category>Event</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Do we need a Community of Open Scholars at Galway?</title>
        <description>Do we need a Community of Open Scholars at Galway?
NUI Galway’s new Open Scholarship Librarian Hardy Schwamm with a few thoughts on an Open Community.
Appetite for Openness?
“Many researchers are interested to adopt Open Science practices in the way they do research.”
This the first statement of the OSC Utrecht About page. I think this is true!
In my previous role at Lancaster University we did a survey and 86 per cent of Lancaster researchers agreed that Open Research should be an institutional priority. I believe the same survey at NUI Galway would produce similar results.

Connecting Open Enthusiasts
In my first few weeks at NUI Galway (I arrived here in mid-August) I have spoken to quite a few researchers who support Open principles in many different ways. However, it appeared that most of them were not connected to each other. In short, there wasn’t a “community”.

So what to do about it?

A model for Galway? Open Science Communities in the Netherlands
The Netherlands are in many ways leading on Open Scholarship (or Open Science as they call it) in Europe. They have a growing network of Open Science Communities (OSCs) with the Open Science Community Utrecht the first (?) and very active. OSC Utrecht have even written a step-by-step tutorial on how to start your own OSC!

The Galway flavour
So looking at the Utrecht OSC model, can we pull off something similar in Galway? I think yes, that seems like a great way to connect Open enthusiasts, share our knowledge and experience and get others on board!

One of the principles we agreed early on is that this is a Community for all of Galway, not just NUI Galway. We are reaching out to other institutions like GMIT and the Marine Institute and are hopeful that we can build a welcoming Community.

More details will emerge after our first meeting on 25 November 2019. This is an exciting initiative with hopefully lots more to come!
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/25/Introducing-the-OSCG/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/10/25/Introducing-the-OSCG/</guid>
        
        <category>post</category>
        
        
        <category>Blog</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
